Guide to the Division of Rare and Manuscripts Games collection, 1890-1999.
Games collection
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Division of Rare and Manuscripts Games collection, 1890-1999.
6554
ca. 7.8 cubic ft.
Games
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Various types of games ranging from historical to contemporary board and card games.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Various types of games ranging from historical to contemporary board and card games. Game titles include: The Adventure Kit of Mathematics, Bingo, The Newlywed Game, Stork Bingo, Scrabble, Monopoly, Happy Families, Old Bachelor; the 90s Version of Old Maid, Flinch, Gumby Colorform Playset, Touring, The Big Board, Architector Jr., Murder at the Missions, Risk, The Fat Albert and the Cosby's Game, Sweet Valley High, African American Discovery, New Town, Marvel Superheroes, Bingo, Old Maid, travel games, Scrabble, Goren's Bridge for 2, Outdoor Survival, Tompkins County Trivia Game, Mental Nuts, Monopoly Deluxe Edition 2002, Monte Carlowe Casino Game Set, and Round the World with Nellie Bly.
Additional games include: The Historiscope, a Panorama and History of America (1868); What Shall I Be? The Exciting Game of Career Girls (1966); Capital Punishment (1981); and Public Assistance (1980) and Twinkees and Trolls. Also, an atomic bomb game from World War II, with a picture of an atomic bomb hurtling toward Japan and two pegs which the player tries to insert in the holes marked Hiroshima and Nagasaki.
SUBJECTS
Subjects:
Board games.; Card games.; Games for travelers.; Paper war games.; Puzzles.; Board games; Card games; Games
Form and genre terms:
Games.; Picture puzzles.; Jigsaw puzzles.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- The Big Board, 1958 (Box 1)
  Play the stocks at home. Includes board, pieces, and fake money
- Monopoly: Deluxe Edition, 1998 (Box 2)
  Never played, still in the plastic
- Architector, Jr., 1945 (Box 3)
  Stone building blocks in red, beige and blue
- Deluxe Monte Carlowe Casino Game Set (Box 4)
  Includes roulette, chuck-a-luck, little bandit, wheel of fortune, horse race, dice, dice layout, chips, and instructions
- TV's Dallas: A Game of the Ewing Family, 1980 (Box 5)
  Game board, play pieces, play cards and money
- The Fat Albert and Cosby Kids Game, 1973 (Box 5)
  Board game with pieces
- Sweet Valley High: Can you find your boyfriend in time for the big date?, 1988 (Box 5)
- Monopoly, 1936 (Box 6)
  Complete game
- African-American Discovery: An Exciting Black History Game, 1990 (Box 6)
  Includes game board and cards
- Newtown Planners' Set, 1972 (Box 6)
  Includes complete set and letter and brochure regarding the game
- Point Count Summary: Goren Official Point Count (Box 6)
  Requirements, responses and rebids. Board looks like a baking sheet made from tin
- Small atomic bomb game from World War II, Undated (Box 6)
- Risk!, 1959 (Box 7)
  Continental game
- Las Vegas Wild, 1954 (Box 7)
  Card tile game
- Round the World With Nellie Bly, 1890 (Box 7)
  Board game with pieces, dial, and instruction booklet
- Tuco Picture Puzzle (Box 8)
  100 piece puzzle of children playing with a toy town
- Tuco Picture Puzzle (Box 8)
  100 piece puzzle of the Lincoln Memorial
- Tuco Picture Puzzle (Box 8)
  100 piece puzzle of the Bill of Rights and onlookers
- Limited Edition American Heritage Jigsaw Puzzle: The Lindbergh Tapestry (Box 8)
  500 piece hand-cut puzzle
- Murder at the Mission, 1984 (Box 8)
  James Swise Mystery game for six people. "Invite your friends, give each a role and a reason to commit murder!"
- Tompkins County Trivial Pursuits cards (Box 8)
- Flinch: A Famous Family Game, 1951 (Box 8)
  Parker Bothers, Inc. card game
- Old Bachelor, 1994 (Box 8)
  The 90's Version of Old Maid
- Happy Families (Box 8)
  Card game, no directions
- Old Maid, 2001 (Box 8)
  Hoyle card game
- Touring: The Famous Automobile Card game, 1954 (Box 8)
  Parker Brothers
- Contack, 1939 (Box 8)
  Triangle card game
- Touring, 1965 (Box 8)
  Parker Brothers Automobile Game
- De Luxe Games (Box 8)
  Boxed set, includes Backgammon, Solitaire peg game, Checkers, and Chinese Checkers
- Deluxe Bingo, 1961 (Box 8)
  Includes 'magic dispenser' and plastic number pieces
- Marvel Superheroes: The Heroic Role-Playing Game, 1984 (Box 8)
  Includes pieces, instructions, and playing board
- Perquackey, 1970 (Box 9)
  Plastic word game
- Mental....Nuts; Can you.......crack 'em?, 1897 (Box 9)
  Trick questions and puzzles booklet
- Tompkins County Trivial Pursuits Cards (Box 9)
  In support of Offender Aid and Restoration of Tompkins County
- Rondo (Box 9)
  Waddingtons Circular Playing Cards
- Russell's Library of Games, 1945 (Box 9)
  Includes miniature versions of card games Old Maid, Authors, Dr. Quack, Slap Jack, Animal Rummy, Crossword
- What's Yours? (Box 9)
  Faulkners 24 questions, each answered with the name of a well-known beverage
- Chit Chat, 1963 (Box 9)
  "The Hugh Downs game of conversation"
- Bridge for Two, 1964 (Box 9)
  Milton Bradley's classic bridge
- The Newlywed Game, 1967 (Box 9)
  Based on the ABC television program
- Gumby Play Set, 1988 (Box 9)
  Includes play pieces and living room play board
- Scrabble, 1953 (Box 9)
  The classic word game
- Stork Bingo, 1957 (Box 9)
  Themed Bingo for a baby shower
- Outdoor Survival, 1972 (Box 9)
  "A game about wilderness skills"
- Brain Quest, 1999 (Box 9)
  A question and answer game for ages 3-4
- Adventure Kit of Mathematics, 1960 (Box 9)
  Includes books and math tools and games
- Multi-game set, ca. 1930 (Box 10)
  Includes instructions and pieces for chess, checkers, poker, roulette, dominoes; lacks checkerboard
- Backgammon set, ca. 1960 (Box 10)
  Includes board
- What Shall I Be? The Exciting Game of Career Girls, 1966 (Box 11)
  Includes board and game pieces
- Public Assistance, 1980 (Box 11)
- Capital Punishment, 1981 (Box 11)
- Twinkees and Trolls, Undated (Box 11)
- The Historiscope: Panorama and History of America, 1868 (Box 12)
  Includes original tickets, crank and narration booklet
- Dr. Ruth's Game of Good Sex, 1985 (Box 13)